[Typewriter Clacking]
[Clacking Continues]
Who is it?
Oh, you're not
intimidated, huh?
Oh, come on, Ken.
You're forgetting that
I'm one half of the world's
greatest mystery writing team.
You, uh, don't have gloves on,
your finger's not on the trigger,
and there are no bullets
in the cylinder.
You're right.
I'm a lousy practical joker.
What are you doing here
with that thing, anyway?
I was on my way down
to the cabin. I thought maybe
I could use it for protection.
Also came by to apologize.
- For what?
- For blowing my cork the other day.
I got out of line.
Forget it.
You know, that happens.
Nah. Shouldn't happen.
Not between you and me.
So, believe it or not, sir,
this is a peace pipe.
Bottoms up, Jim.
In the middle
of the morning?
Oh, come on. Relax.
It's Saturday.
And in the mystery writer's soul,
it is always the middle of the night.
Oh! A toast.
Dear sir,
I give you...
our divorce.
Well, it's not really
a divorce.
Oh, sure it is.
Come on. Let's be honest.
I mean, it's...
There's no alimony, but, uh,
it is a termination.
Ah, yes.
And our dear little children.
All 1 5 of them.
Fifty million copies.
And to the lady who made it all possible,
the greatest sleuth in the world,
Mrs. Melville,
whom we brought to life
and now we're about to bury.
Come on, Ken.
You're making me feel guilty.
All I want to do is write on my own.
You're right.
I am being selfish.
Okay, my boy.
My blessings on your solo flight.
Thanks.
I appreciate it.
After all, friendship is more important
than partnership. Right?
Here's to our friendship.
Right.
And now, sir,
I'm gonna kidnap you.
What?
The aforementioned cabin...
which has been finished
for over six months now...
You haven't seen it.
You're gonna be
my first male guest.
Oh, I can't, Ken. Not now.
Well, why can't you?
It's all the way down
in San Diego.
Oh, it's a couple of hours' drive.
I'll have you home
before midnight.
Yeah, well, I promised Joanna
I'd take her to dinner
and a show.
Aw, that's easy. You pick up that phone,
you say, ' Honey, I'm gonna be working
late at the office tonight." Come on.
Soon as we get down there,
we uncork another bottle,
and then we go fishing.
Well, I...
You know what your trouble,
old buddy is...
I mean, you're afraid
to unwind even for a day.
Oh, no, I'm not.
Well, then, prove it.
Come on. If you want
some justification,
you're doing it
as a favor for me.
At least give me a chance
to bury the hatchet
with some style, huh?
You just don't drop your partner,
then turn down his invitation
all in one week, now do you?
Actually, the timing isn't bad.
I was just finishing the final chapter.
Ah, Mrs. Melville's last case.
You know, we ought to send
that broad some flowers.
Listen, I made a list of things
I'd like to take from the office.
You want to take
a look at it?
I don't get it.
It's a list of names.
Oh, I'm losing my mind.
It's the wrong one.
I must have left the other one
at the house.
Uh... Oh, I am
losing my mind.
What's the matter?
I left my lighter
in the office.
Do you need it?
That's my security blanket.
I'll only be a minute.
dd [Whistling]
And to think I had to
talk you into this trip.
Ah, Jim, smell that air.
How far is the cabin?
Ah, it's not far.
About an hour.
We have to skirt San Diego.
I'll only be a minute.
I just have to get some supplies.
Do you want to hand me that book
in that glove compartment?
Hey, it's one of ours.
[Chuckles]
Yeah.
The boss lady here's
a big fan of ours.
I've been promising this for months.
[Chuckles]
The price of fame.
You want me to come with you?
No, no.
I'll only be a minute.
Miss La Sanka!
Anybody home?
In a minute!
Mr. Franklin!
Oh, my planets must be
in the right house!
[Chuckles]
Not only that,
but they're working overtime.
I have a surprise for you.
Pour moi?
Pour moi.
Prescription: Murder.
'A Mrs. Melville thriller...
byJames Ferris
and Ken Franklin."
Oh, uh, take a look
at the first page.
You signed it?
You dear man.
Well, Mr. Franklin!
I'd rather have the storyteller
than the story.
Well, I'll tell you what.
If you play your cards right
and give me my grocery list,
someday you may have both.
Empty promises.
Miss La Sanka!
What do you need?
Just a few things
for overnight, thanks.
Who is it this week?
The blonde or the redhead?
Uh, Miss La Sanka,
I'm all alone this weekend.
Except for, uh, some
contemplation, some fishing
and a refreshment of my spirit.
Could you break this for me?
I need some change for the phone.
Thanks very much.
[Cash Register Dings]
That'll do fine.
Thank you.
Operator, I'd like to place
a station-to-station call
to Los Angeles.
The area code is 213.
[Phone Ringing]
Hello.
Joanna, it's Ken.
Well, Ken! I thought
you werert talking to us.
Oh, that's all patched up.
As a matter of fact,
I leftJim at the office
a few hours ago.
- We signed the armistice.
- Oh, well, that's a relief.
Look, Joanna,
I wouldn't mention it to him.
I'm sure he'd like to
surprise you himself.
Uh, why don't you
join us for dinner?
We'll celebrate.
I'd really love to, but I'm...
I'm spending the weekend
down here in San Diego
at the cabin.
As a matter of fact,
that's where I'm calling from.
All right. Then we'll
do it another time.
Absolutely.
Uh, Joanna, I thought maybe if you,
for some reason, needed to get
in touch with me, you do know
the number at the cabin.
Right.
I'll see you in a few days.
Fine.
Good-bye.
Did you ever get a feeling
of déjà vu?
What?
Like you've, uh, done something before,
but you know you haven't.
Why?
What do you mean?
I'm getting it right now.
It's strange.
You know I've never
been here before.
Maybe in a previous
incarnation, huh?
Ken, it's fantastic.
The house
that Mrs. Melville built.
Wait till you see
the inside.
[Sighs]
It's no wonder.
'No wonder" what?
What woman could resist
this setting?
Not very many.
I promise you that.
How about a drink, Jim?
More alcohol?
No, thanks.
It'll corrupt me.
[Chuckles]
You're thinking
aboutJoanna, aren't you?
Well, yeah.
You know,
just taking off like that.
She still expects me for dinner.
We can fix that.
We'll put plan ' A" into effect.
Pick up the phone
and call her.
What am I gonna tell her?
The man is too square
for words.
Now, look. You simply say
that you're working
at the office.
You're calling from the office.
She knows you have a deadline to meet
with the book. You're working late.
How many times
have you had to do that?
A couple hundred, I guess.
Exactly.
That's why she'll believe you.
Yeah, well, I...
I just hate lying
to her. You know.
You're not lying to her.
You're saving her
a little anguish.
Now, will you pick up the phone
and call her so we can
start enjoying ourselves?
Okay.
- Oh, Operator, I'd like to
make a collect...
- Hold it.
It's a cinch you have never
cheated on Joanna before.
If you want your wife to believe
you're calling from the office,
you don't have the operator
place the call... you dial it direct.
The area code is 213.
Hi, honey.
How are ya?
Well, that's what
I'm calling about.
Um, I'm at the office, and...
I'm pretty well into
this last chapter.
I'd like to work straight through.
Yeah, I know.
L... I know.
This'll be the last time.
That I can...
[Shot Fires]
Jimmy?
Jimmy!
Operator, get me the police.
[Phone Ringing]
Hello. Joanna?
What?
Joanna...
Will you take it easy?
Now, say it again once more.
Are you sure?
Did you call the police?
Yes, yes, of course.
I'll leave right away.
Uh, Joanna, please.
Take it easy.
And don't worry.
I'm sure it's nothing
but a practical joke.
Good-bye.
No, I know it's insane.
And l-l-I just... I keep
thinking of the clichés and-and...
Jim and Ken
wrote this scene...
in their books a hundred times.
Look at it this way, Mrs. Ferris.
Maybe he isn't dead.
Now, there's no body,
no blood...
No! He was shot!
L-I know it!
L-l-I heard...
I heard it on the phone.
Are you sure
it was a gunshot?
This place was searched.
- Papers on the floor.
Have you any idea why?
- No, I have no idea why.
Did you notice
anything special missing?
No, no, no.
Are you sure it was his voice?
[Joanna]
Yes, I know it was his voice,
and maybe somebody...
[Man]
Was he under any kind
of extra pressure?
[Joanna]
No. Maybe somebody was...
- Did he say where he was calling from?
- Yes.
He said he was calling
from the office. He said... He said...
"I'm calling from the office."
I really don't care
if anything was missing.
I just really want to find out
what happened to my husband.
We'll do our best.
You sure it was his voice?
I know it was his voice.
Are you sure it was a gunshot?
Yes, that's right.
[Man] Would you like to sit down
and get a glass of water?
Yes, I would like...
Really, please.
'Cause I really feel stupid,
and I just really
want to clear my head.
Get the water.
Okay.
[Columbo]
I think that's out of order, ma'am.
Uh, you see, that's the trouble
with these buildings.
The fountains never work.
Then you have to use
the coffee machine.
And then you lose your dime
and the coffee's lousy.
Who are you?
Uh, I'm just another cop.
My name's Columbo.
I'm a lieutenant.
Were you in there...
I got the proof right here.
You didn't see me in there
because I left before you got in there.
And you know why?
Because it's so smoky in there
and so noisy in there...
that I just had to come outside
and get a breath.
Oh, I think I'd better get back.
Now, look.
Wait a minute.
Let me tell you something.
You look very tired to me,
and I think you had
a terrible experience in there.
And I think
I ought to drive you home.
Let's call it a night.
Well, don't you think
they want to ask me questions?
Oh, I don't think they'll mind.
I think you've answered
enough questions,
and I'll call them
and I'll tell them you're with me.
Okay?
Well, what about Ken?
Why isn't Ken here?
I don't know why he isn't here.
Is that Mr. Franklin,
the other half of the writing team?
[Chuckles]
Yeah, the other half
of the team.
You know, that's what I like
about these buttons.
You don't have to push 'em.
They go off with the heat
of your hand.
I bet you haven't had
anything to eat.
You're a very nice man, Lieutenant,
but I'm not really hungry.
I'll tell you, Mrs. Ferris,
I'm the worst cook in the world.
But there's one thing I do terrific,
and that's an omelet.
Even my wife admits it.
Uh, I need something for the eggshells.
- Over there in that cabinet.
- Right.
I'm really not hungry.
Listen.
You take a taste.
You don't like it,
you throw it away.
I'll tell you what the secret is
to a good omelet.
- No eggs. Just milk.
- [Stifled Chuckle]
- Uh, skillet.
- Over there.
You're a very persuasive man,
Lieutenant.
Maybe I should hold up my end
and make the coffee.
I need cheese and onions
and, uh, butter.
Cheese... Uh, I need something
to grate the cheese.
Over there in the cupboard.
Right.
What did they do with him,
Lieutenant?
I don't know, ma'am.
Well, there was no body in the office.
Couldn't that mean that he isn't dead?
Well, that's hard to say.
Uh, it's bothering me too.
I tell ya, the whole thing
doesn't make sense
unless it's a kidnapping.
Well, you don't shoot
a victim first, do you?
Why'd you laugh before?
When?
When I asked you if Mr. Franklin was
the other half of the writing team.
Did I laugh?
Yep.
Maybe it was the way you put it.
'Writing team."
Maybe I shouldn't say it,
but Ken hasn't written a word
of a Mrs. Melville novel in years.
Mrs. Melville?
Who's Mrs. Melville?
The character
thatJim and Ken created.
The one who solves
all the crimes brilliantly.
Well, uh, why did your husband
put up with it?
What I mean is, uh,
him doing all the work.
Well, there were compensations.
Ken did the publicity,
went on all the talk shows,
and he did interviews
and cultivated the film people.
He contributed.
He just didn't do
any of the writing.
Boy, I'll tell ya,
I'd love to be a writer.
That's a terrific talent.
Where did he get
all the ideas?
Oh, from almost anything.
People. Magazines.
Conversations.
I'm constantly finding
scraps of paper
and old matchbook covers...
just all over the house
with notes and ideas.
And those were mysteries, too,
werert they, huh?
Mm-hmm.
They're tricky.
I'll tell you that.
I could never
figure those things out.
Well, it got harder.
Maybe that's why he decided
to go out on his own.
Oh, really? I didn't know that.
I guess he wanted to do
some serious work.
No kidding?
How did Mr. Franklin take that?
Not very well.
But he'll get over it.
Gee, I'd hate to be in his shoes.
Why?
Well, you got a writing team, and they're
very famous, and now they break up,
and what happens?
One fella continues writing books,
and the other fella just stops.
Yeah. That's what
I keep telling Jim...
that sooner or later,
people are bound to find out.
What, that your husband
did all the writing?
Mmm.
Yeah.
Kind of tough
on Mr. Franklirs ego.
[Doorbell Rings]
Oh, Ken!
Jo.
I know, I know.
Just take it easy.
I drove up here
as fast as I could.
Is there anything new?
No, not yet.
Jo, it's incredible.
I just saw him
this morning at the office.
Oh, I'm sorry, Ken.
Uh,
Lieutenant Columbo,
Mr. Franklin.
How you doir?
No, the question is,
how you doing, Lieutenant?
Well, I'm afraid
we just got started.
Has Jim been found yet?
Has he been found yet?
Uh...
Why? Did somebody tell you
he was gone?
Lieutenant, I just spent several hours
driving up here from San Diego.
You must know that this story
is on every news station.
Oh, right. Yeah.
Gee, I should have thought of that.
Well, has he been found?
Gee, I'm afraid not.
No. Were you visiting friends
in San Diego?
He has a place there... a cabin.
Oh, away for the weekend.
Gee, that's nice.
Mmm. Could we get back
to my question?
Have you come up with
any leads, any clues?
Uh, it's a little early for that.
Early?
Seems to me your men are
standing around just marking time.
Could I have a drink, love?
I could use one myself.
Thanks.
I'll tell you something,
Lieutenant.
See, if Mrs. Melville
were on this case,
oh, she'd be leaps and bounds
ahead of you by now.
Is that the lady in the books?
That's right.
You see, she would have
figured out that this is not
just someone missing.
This is a professional killing.
Aha. Here it is.
Take a look at that.
Uh, put it on the desk.
Just drop it. 'Cause of
the fingerprints, you know.
Jim's fingerprints
are all over that.
So are mine.
What is it?
What's it look like?
It's a list of names.
Look at that. Mustel,
Delgado, Hathaway, Westlake...
Sound familiar?
Uh, yeah, kinda.
Well, they should. That's a list
of some of the top men
in organized crime on the West Coast...
L.A., Vegas, Frisco...
I don't understand.
Well, it's painfully obvious.
One of these men
had Jim killed.
Really? Why?
Tell me something.
How long have you been
a lieutenant, Lieutenant?
Mrs. Melville would have
put that together like that.
[Snaps Fingers]
Look, I... I'm willing to take
all the help I can get.
All right. Let me see
if I can explain it to you.
See, my partner and I
decided to split,
go our separate ways.
I'm sureJoanna must have
mentioned that to you.
Yeah, she said
something about that.
Did she also mention the fact
thatJim wanted to do
some serious writing?
Hey.
Uh-huh. Uh-huh.
Wait a minute. Yeah!
Dawning on you now?
I knew you'd get it.
But that's only
the tip of the iceberg.
You see, Jim was researching
a complete and factual exposé...
of all West Coast organized crime.
I mean, he was going around asking
some pretty embarrassing questions.
Probing.
Compiling dossiers.
That's why
they searched this office.
Apparently, they got everything
but that list.
And you think one of these fellas
put out a contract on him.
Of course. Word must have gotten around
thatJim was compiling all this information.
They knew they couldn't buy him off,
so what do they do?
They chose the usual
alternative.
Professional killing, huh?
But if that's true,
why did they get rid of the body?
Well, who knows?
But remember one thing...
Without a corpus delicti,
you can't prove a murder
was committed in the first place.
But why would
a professional killer care?
I mean, he's already on a plane
back from where he came.
Lieutenant, I can't answer
all your questions. I've given you
a list of the most likely suspects.
A clear motive.
Isn't that enough to start with?
Oh, that's plenty.
And believe me, I'm very grateful
for all the help you've given me.
Gee, that's funny.
What?
Well, this thing is folded lengthwise,
like someone was carrying it
in their pocket.
So?
Well, if he typed that
on that typewriter...
and I'll run a check on that...
why would he fold it up
before he put it in that drawer?
[Chuckling]
I'm beginning to like you.
Why is that?
Because you're finally beginning
to think like Mrs. Melville.
Unfortunately, Jim used to
fold up a piece of paper,
and he'd use it
as a bookmark, you know.
Ah.
Now, however interesting
your observation is,
it only leads us far astray.
However,
since you are beginning to learn
how to emulate our dear lady,
I'm gonna give you something
that you richly deserve...
a chance to read
some of our books.
Well, that's very nice of you.
Didn't expect gifts tonight, huh?
Thank you. Maybe I can
pick up a few pointers.
Oh, I'm sure you can.
Uh, could you handle
some more?
Oh, all right.
Here you go.
Oh, and an extra.
Oh, that's very nice.
That ought to keep you busy
for a while, huh?
Yeah, it sure will.
Well, anything else, Lieutenant?
Uh, no, I don't think so.
I think I'd better let you
get some sleep.
Oh, that's very nice of you.
I just only hope
I was of some help.
Oh, you certainly were.
Well, good night, Lieutenant.
Good night, sir.
Good night.
Oh, Mr. Franklin. Uh...
Actually, uh, there is one thing,
not that it makes
that much difference.
What is it?
When Mrs. Ferris called you
and told you her husband got shot,
you jumped in a car and drove
right back to L.A.
Is that right?
That's right.
You know, me,
I'd have taken a plane.
I mean, it's a big airport,
and they run every half hour.
It'd been a lot faster.
Well, I... That's true,
but in a situation like that,
who thinks clearly?
And look at it this way.
You add up all the time it takes
to drive to and from an airport,
how much time
do you really save?
Hmm.
Operator, would you get me
the police, please?
Thank you.
Lt. Columbo, please.
Yes, thank you.
I'll wait.
Columbo, this is Franklin.
I think you better get over here
right away.
937 Skyview Drive.
It's an emergency.
[Woman On Police Radio: Indistinct]
[Woman on Radio]
1- L 10. MPs have been notified.
Do you still request
a radio unit?
[Man On Radio]
All units in the vicinity,
a prowler, 12F3...
[Fades]
When I got home, there he...
there it was, right
in the middle of the lawn.
Terrible thing to come home to.
The funny thing is, I...
I kept hoping or I...
I was sure thatJim was still alive.
PoorJoanna.
Every time I think of
feeling sorry for myself,
I think of how much
she had to lose.
Look at 'em!
Vultures!
Lieutenant, you mind
if I go inside? I...
can't stand
to watch them... gape.
Listen. You mind
if I come with you?
Because there's no lining
in this coat, and I'm a bit chilly.
I don't mind.
[Phone Ringing]
Hello.
Yes, this is Mr. Franklin.
What? No comment.
Aw, you've gotta be kidding.
You want an interview now?
A gentleman of the press.
Afraid you're gonna get
a lot of that.
I'm sorry, Lieutenant.
I'm forgetting my manners.
Would you like a drink?
Yeah. Mmm.
Maybe a drop ofbourbon.
Bourbon.
Boy, this is quite a place.
This a copy?
Hardly.
It's an original.
Gee, I thought they only
hung this stuff on museums.
You own this?
Mrs. Melville has been very kind.
Boy. Quite a place.
Gee whiz. And you got
that other place in San Diego.
Gee, the upkeep alone must be...
I manage to scrape by.
Your drink.
Thank you. You know,
there's one thing about writers
that I don't understand.
Maybe you can help me
clear it up.
If a fella's partner dies,
uh, does he own the other
fella's half of the books,
half of the, uh, um...
Royalties?
Yeah.
No. They go
into the deceased's estate.
Mmm. That leaves you
out in the cold, doesn't it?
Unless, of course,
you insured each other.
Lieutenant, aren't we going
a bit far astray?
You're right. We shouldn't
be talking about this now.
It's not the time.
Uh... Uh...
So, Mr. Franklin, tell me, uh,
why do you think that they left
your partner's body out there
on the lawn like that?
Do you mean to tell me
you haven't figured that out?
Lieutenant,
you disappoint me.
It was left as a warning.
A warning?
Of course.
It also proves my theory about
it being a professional killing.
See, the moment they dropped
Jim's body in the middle
of that lawn...
Please, sit down.
You know
what they were saying?
That this could happen to you...
unless you stop
in your partner's research.
- They're trying to scare you.
- Exactly.
Right.
So what are you gonna do?
Are you gonna continue
writing the book anyway?
No, that's the irony of it.
You see, that was Jim's
pet project, not mine.
[Chuckles]
I wouldn't even know
where to begin.
Say, I guess they didn't have
any way of knowing
you two were gonna split up.
Nah. Even if they did,
it wouldn't have doneJim any good.
I must say, Lieutenant,
you're up against a dead end.
Look at this.
You got a body,
you got a motive,
but you're never
gonna find that killer.
It's not gonna be easy.
I'll lay you 5 to 1
it was someone
in Las Vegas or Miami.
Picked up a phone and...
pfft! ...put out a contract.
Right. Right.
How you're gonna make a case,
much less solve one,
is beyond me.
I know. I guess the only thing
I can do is... just check out
every name on that list.
Sure. You know what's gonna
happen? Every one of those guys
is gonna deny thatJim even existed.
Right.
I must say
I don't envy you.
I don't envy myself.
Now, look. I got a lot
of phone calls to make.
I'd better get on it, huh?
All the luck.
Thanks. Thanks a lot,
Mr. Franklin.
And listen. I'm very sorry
about what happened tonight.
Thank you.
Right.
You, uh...
You will keep me posted,
Lieutenant?
Oh, yes, I will. Yeah.
You know, there's only one thing
that I'm not clear about.
But that can wait.
You want to go to bed.
Lieutenant, I'm not gonna
get any sleep anyway.
What is it?
Would you go over for me
once again... I know you did it...
exactly what happened
when you came home tonight?
Sure. L...
I've already told you, but...
[Sighs]
The moment I saw Jim's body
in the middle of the lawn,
I came running in here
and I picked up the phone
and I called you.
I mean, it's a purely
reflexive action.
Uh-huh. Right. Uh-huh.
Uh-huh. That's fine.
Now, wait a minute.
You look like you're troubled.
Is there some reason
for your question?
Uh, it's your mail.
My mail?
Isn't it funny
how people are different?
Now, me, if I found my partner dead,
I'd never think of opening my letters.
But I-I... I just did it
to distract myself.
I mean, you got to remember
one thing, that's a great shock.
Yeah.
Oh, that's understandable.
And bills are distracting.
Listen, if anything comes up,
I'll call you right away.
Good night.
I'm gonna have a hot dog.
I guess I will too.
No, no, Mr. Tucker.
You put that away.
This one's on me.
May I have a receipt, please?
All right, Lieutenant.
You're bribing me
with a handsome lunch.
What can I do for you?
Uh, this is about
an insurance policy.
Oh, excellent.
It's about time you came to me.
I can give you
a package within your...
Yeah, this is, uh,
an insurance policy
that was already written.
Oh, this is official business.
Uh, yeah.
Uh, there are two mystery writers...
Ken Franklin and James Ferris.
Your company
wrote a policy on them?
Now, wait a minute, Lieutenant.
We like to cooperate
with the police, but...
if you want confidential information,
I'm afraid that you...
Oh, well, look, uh,
I don't want to cause you any trouble.
Maybe it'll be more helpful
if I got a court order?
[Chattering]
[Chattering Continues]
Oh, Ken, it was simply marvelous.
I was terrified.
Oh, really?
I had the whole thing figured out
by the end of the first act.
Oh, you did?
I was completely fooled.
You must have a devious mind.
No, dear,
it's because you're young.
Always remember
one thing, my love.
The moment
a man mentions a long-lost twin,
you can inevitably know that it's
going to be some impersonation.
It's an old plot trick.
Mr. Franklin! Yoo-hoo!
- Over here!
- Who's that?
Someone
that should be somewhere else.
[Man]
No, we go this way.
Excuse me a moment.
Miss La Sanka,
what a pleasant surprise.
Hi. [Giggling]
What brings you to the big city?
Oh, I came in to do
a little shopping.
You... You like my dress?
Oh, it's lovely.
See a play.
[Laughs]
She's a beauty,
Mr. Franklin.
Yes, she is.
Uh, thank you.
I haven't seen her before
have I?
No, I don't believe you have.
Well, it's...
it's lovely to see you.
I, uh,
hope you won't think
I'm being forward,
[Chuckles]
But is there any chance of, uh,
our having a drink together?
Oh, I'd... I'd love to, really.
But, uh...
See, the young lady and I
are going to have a late supper.
I think you might want to cancel it.
- Just why would I want to do that?
- Because...
we really should have a discussion.
[Chuckles]
Perhaps some other time.
All right. L...
I suppose I'll have to find
someone else to tell my story to.
[Chuckles]
It's a mystery story.
Very interesting.
Really.
It's all about this witness.
[Chuckles]
Just wait here.
I'll be right back.
Anything you say, Mr. Franklin.
d [Piano]
[Laughing]
Oh, wow!
Oh, I just can't resist
strawberries.
Oh, I'm glad you like them.
[Giggling]
[Giggling Continues]
You're...
You're making me nervous.
That's quite a stare.
I'm sorry.
L-I can't help it.
You know,
I've never seen you outside
that store before.
You're very lovely.
May I call you Lili?
Yes, please do.
[Giggles]
How did you enjoy
the play tonight?
Oh, I thought
it was predictable. You?
Oh, I like your books
much more.
That's very flattering.
But you said something before
about, uh,
about your story
or something about a...
a witness.
Oh, yes. Well, actually,
it's a, uh,
true-to-life story.
Oh, the best kind.
[Giggles]
It concerns your partner.
Jim?
Uh-huh.
What about him?
Well, I read in the papers
about his death,
and I felt just terrible.
Thank you.
I felt just terrible, because they said
he was killed in his office.
So they did.
Well,
in my story, you see,
he couldn't have actually
been killed in an office,
because he was, uh,
somewhere else.
Just for a moment,
let's forget about your story,
and let's, uh...
let's talk about real life.
[Chuckles]
It is simpler, isn't it?
Much.
I'll tell you honestly, Ken.
I was very confused
when I saw the papers,
because,
when you were in my store
making a phone call the other day,
Uh-huh.
I wandered over
to the side window to see...
if you had brought a lady with you.
[Giggles]
You didn't believe me when I said
that I was alone.
Oh, I believed you.
It's just that...
I'm very interested in you, Ken.
[Giggles]
Well, anyway,
you can imagine my surprise
when I saw your partner.
There he was, big as life,
sitting there
in the front seat of your car.
And that disturbed you, huh?
Oh, not at that time.
Only later.
And then I debated
with myself for days...
whether to come
and see you or not.
Why didn't you go to the police?
Oh, Ken.
I wouldn't want
to get you into trouble.
[Giggling]
Of course not.
[Snorting Chuckle]
All right, Lili. How much?
[Laughs]
I hope you don't think that
that's the on...
Oh, no, no, no.
I don't think anything.
I'll tell you something.
I'm most grateful you came to me first.
Know why?
Because I think we can reach
an equitable agreement.
I do so admire your candor.
This isn't easy for me...
a widow running a...
small country store,
trying to make ends meet.
Oh, I can understand that.
And I also recognize in you
a woman of... of some breeding.
I mean, you're not just
a common... blackmailer.
I'm so glad you're understanding.
Very well, Lili.
How much for your silence?
$15,000? L...
[Plate Clattering]
Oh! L-I know it's a lot,
but that's all I'll ever ask for.
Honestly.
- And I'm a woman of my word!
- I know you are, and I respect you for that.
And you know what?
In that spirit, I accept your terms.
Agreed?
[Relieved Chuckle]
Agreed.
[Chuckles]
And I know you won't take offense
when I say,
'It's a pleasure
doing business with you."
No, no. My pleasure.
[Chuckles]
[Both Chuckling]
- [Chuckling Continues]
- [Doorbell Chiming]
Yes?
Is Mr. Franklin home?
He's occupied at the moment.
Who shall I say is calling?
Uh, Lt. Columbo.
Oh. Well, won't you
come in and wait?
Thank you.
He'll be with you shortly.
[Camera Shutter Clicking]
[Man]
Only a few more.
Thanks muchly, Mr. Franklin.
I think we're about finished,
if you can bear
one or two more photographs.
Fire away.
After all, your magazine
was very kind to Franklin and Ferris
during our lean years.
That's, uh, the second reason
I granted the interview.
Oh? What was the first?
- Why, the charm
of the interviewer, of course.
- Thank you.
- [Thump]
- [Shutter Clicks]
Yes, Lieutenant.
Is there something I can do for you?
Oh, yeah. If-lf you...
If you have a moment.
That's about all I do have.
As soon as I finish here,
I'll be right with you.
Is there anything else, Miss, uh...
May I call you Gloria?
Please do.
Uh, just one last question.
I think our readers will want to know
how the death of your partner will affect
the Mrs. Melville books.
I'm afraid when I buried Jim
I buried Mrs. Melville with him.
Mmm, I understand.
But everyone will miss her so.
Can't you write another one?
Oh, I could, naturally,
but what's the point?
With Jim gone, there...
[Smacks Lips]
Wouldn't be much reason.
No, I'm afraid, uh,
Mrs. Melville has solved
her last case.
Actually, I've been...
seriously debating as to whether
I would ever want to write again.
Oh, well, I hope you do.
Thank you.
That's very kind of you.
Now, if you don't mind, huh?
Of course.
Let's go Harvey.
Perhaps,
under better circumstances,
I, uh...
less harassed circumstances...
I could give you a more detailed interview.
- Even in more depth.
- Mmm, that'll be nice.
Shall I call you?
Yes. Please do.
Next week, huh?
Good-bye.
Oh, sorry, Harvey.
Thanks, very much.
Thank you.
All right, Lieutenant.
What can I do for you?
Well, I brought back your books.
Well, that's fine.
Just put 'em over there
on the table.
Yeah. Uh, sure.
I wanted to tell ya how much
I enjoyed 'em.
I think they're the most terrific...
Boy, I wanna...
And... Oh, listen, I'll come back.
I'll make two trips on this.
But the... the lady detective...
What a character, what a brain.
And what logic!
The way she figures it out!
Lieutenant.
I'd love to sit down
and discuss literature with you,
but I was on my way out.
Oh. Oh, I'm sorry.
I didn't mean to bother ya.
Uh, you goir someplace special?
Yes, as a matter of fact.
I'm on my way down to my cabin
for a rest.
- Would you like an itinerary?
- Hey, I'm sorry.
- I'm makir a pest of myself.
- No.
Yes, yes, I am.
I know, it's because I keep
askir these questions.
But I'll tell ya.
I can't help myself.
It's a habit.
I take it you're not goir alone.
- Whatever gave that idea?
- I noticed the two bottles of champagne.
Oh, those. Oh, I'm quite capable
of drinking those two bottles...
and a good deal more
without any help.
Now, if you'll excuse me,
Lieutenant.
Yeah. Uh, listen.
Unless you just wanna take a second...
to know how we're progressir
on your partner's list.
Oh?
Anything concrete?
No, not a thing.
Just like you predicted.
Everyone said
they never even heard ofJames Ferris.
[Smacks Lips]
That's just as I expected.
Well, it was lovely to chat with you,
Lieutenant.
Oh, Mr. Franklin?
Do you have a minute?
Yeah.
Is it important?
Well, it could be.
You see, I was checking the, uh,
the phone company records
in San Diego.
Now, why would you want
to do that, Lieutenant?
Oh, well, I have to do that.
You know, that's part of my job.
I got to tie up all those loose ends.
Anyway,
on the day of the murder...
there was a record
of a call from the cabin.
It was a call to the Ferris house
in Los Angeles.
I see.
And now you're wondering whether
I can explain that. Is that right?
Oh, I'm sure you can.
Oh, you're right. I can.
But, you see, you would've saved
both you and me a great deal of trouble...
if you'd checked
with Joanna Ferris first.
She would've explained to you
that I'd spoken with her from my cabin,
telling her thatJim and I had
patched up our differences.
Oh, what do you mean
by ' differences"? Uh...
Well, you see,
ironing out any difficulties
in a separation is never easy.
And I knew Joanna would be concerned,
and I wanted to put her mind at ease.
Oh, I see.
Can you understand that?
Oh, yes. Yeah, that's understandable.
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Oh, fine. Is that all?
Yes, that's all. Right.
Good.
[Snickers]
Listen, uh,
enjoy your trip.
Thanks very much.
And drive carefully.
[Engine Starts]
Don't worry, Lieutenant.
You can count on it.
And... here you are!
[Laughs]
Bearing gifts.
And more gifts.
Why, Mr. Franklin, how lovely.
[Chuckles]
Ken.
Yes, of course. Ken.
Now, Lili, let me ask
you a simple question.
You up to making a nice,
quiet dinner for two tonight?
d [Orchestra: Romantic]
Here's to... prosperity.
And romance.
[Both Chuckling]
A daily double.
[Laughing]
Oh, I must say, Lili,
that was a magnificent meal.
Where'd you learn
to cook so well?
My late husband,
may he rest in peace,
was a professional chef.
Wonderful man.
[Chuckles]
He taught me all I know.
Well, he taught you well.
Thank you, sir.
Refill?
Oh, sorry.
Oop!
We're all out.
[Laughs]
Let's open another one.
Dare we?
Dare we not?
Mm-hmm!
Here we go. Happy New Year!
[Cork Pops]
[Both Laughing]
Quick, the glass.
[Laughing Continues]
Oh! Mmm!
Delicious!
But I'm afraid
I'm getting a little tipsy.
What's wrong with that?
[Slurred]
I don't know if I can trust you.
Now,
is there any reason not to?
Lili, if I make you uncomfortable,
I can always leave.
No. Please.
I do enjoy your company.
You know what we should do?
What?
It's such a beautiful night,
we should...
row out
to the center of the lake and...
go for a swim.
Mmm.
Sounds nice.
Mmm. Is nice. Shall we?
Better not.
Why not?
I trust you, Ken.
Really.
But we all have
our dark sides, don't we?
Just wouldn't be very intelligent of me
to be alone with you in a small boat.
After all, you might start having
second thoughts about the money.
I wish
you hadrt said that, Lili.
That kind of talk
hurts me deeply.
I'm gonna tell you something,
and I shouldn't.
But I'll tell you why,
because I trust you.
I was prepared to give you
considerably more than you asked for.
Fifteen thousand... I mean,
I've lost that much gambling
in one night.
Well, it certainly
is a great deal of money to me.
What do you think you'll, uh...
you'll do with all of it?
I don't know.
Put it in the bank, I guess.
But not right away.
Ohh!
I just want to look at it for awhile.
[Chuckles]
d [Continues]
Better be careful.
Someone might, uh,
rob you.
I'll just keep it for a day or two.
I've never seen
so much money in my life.
Uh,
maybe...
maybe you could take a...
a trip somewhere, huh?
I may. I've always
wanted to go on a cruise.
Oh, cruises,
they're so romantic.
Did I tell you that my late husband
was in the merchant marines?
Is that a fact?
Mmm.
They're the ones
who taught him how to cook.
I almost wish he were here now.
He could share this with me.
Or maybe we can do
the next best thing.
[No Audio]
Who did you say it is?
One of the cops said
it was a local woman.
Some kind of drowning.
[Woman On Police Radio]
Twelve A-15, clear.
Twelve A-17, are you clear?
Twelve A-1, clear.
Twelve A-15, stand by.
One L-10, M.P. S have been notified.
dd [Whistling]
dd [Stops]
Mornir!
Well, Lt. Columbo.
I must say, you turn up
at the oddest times, don't you?
Listen, I hope you don't mind
my comir in that way, you know.
But the door was open,
and I just let myself in.
Oh, no.
How'd you get here? By magic carpet?
I didn't see your car outside.
Oh, no. I pulled around back,
and I put it in the shade.
You know,
the sun raises hell with the paint.
Oh, sensible.
Well, what brings you
up here to the wilds?
Well, I'll tell ya.
I heard you and Mrs. Ferris talk
so much about this place,
and you made it sound so terrific,
and believe me, uh,
you werert exaggerating,
because...
this is magnificent.
And, uh, since I got
a two-week vacation comir up,
I said to myself, ' Go on down there,
check out the area, look to see.
Mmm.
Maybe you can rent a cabin."
Lieutenant, you're not gonna tell me
you drove down here just to look
for a vacation spot, are you?
Why else would I come?
You're wasting your time.
I have a feeling that cabins
in this neck of the woods are pretty much
out of your price range, anyway.
Most of them are...
are rented for the season.
Oh, gee whiz, that's...
that's too bad.
Gosh, my wife
is gonna be disappointed.
Well, it was a nice ride, anyhow.
Yes, a lovely drive.
Except for that
bottleneck down the road.
What was that all about?
Oh, there was a drowning.
Well, what was it,
a fisherman?
Well, I heard someone say
it was a local woman.
Uh, a Miss La Sanka
or something like that?
Something like that, yeah.
Yeah. Did you know her?
Not really, no.
I was just wondering, because,
when I was in the kitchen before,
I noticed a grocery box
with her name on it.
Oh, I occasionally buy supplies
there, sure, like anyone else
who lives around here.
Uh-huh.
I think she was the one
that drowned. Yeah.
'Cause I, uh, stopped by
the grocery store on the way here
to pick up some cigars,
and I noticed it was closed
and the cops'cars around.
Well, if it was her,
I... I'd be very sorry.
She was always very friendly.
Yeah, that's a shame.
Mm-hmm.
[Sucks Teeth]
Oh, you did know her.
Lieutenant, I know a lot of people
without really knowing them.
You know, like barbers,
waitresses, parking lot attendants,
even the cop on the beat.
Don't you?
Yeah. [Chuckling]
Yeah, I do, matter of fact.
I'll tell you, though.
People are strange.
You know, I can't figure 'em out.
Why a woman goes out on a lake
all by herself...
before the light comes up.
Oh, there's nothing
unusual about that.
A lot of us go out early.
It's peaceful
and kind of makes
you feel like you're...
plugged into nature.
Mmm.
Know what I mean?
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, say, listen.
Look, you came down here...
to get away from things,
and I'm just takir up your time.
I didn't mean to bother you.
No, no, no.
It's no bother at all.
Say, I'd be more than glad
to let you have a bathing suit,
but, uh, you don't look like
the athletic type to me.
Well, it's, uh, my wife
that's the athlete.
Oh?
Yeah.
So, you don't think I'm gonna
be able to find a cabin to rent, huh?
Mmm.
Best bet is to go down and check
with some of the local real estate people.
Uh-huh.
Because I think it'd be fun
to be neighbors for a couple of weeks.
[Chuckles]
[Laughs] Y-Yeah.
Say, what kind of nightlife
do you have around here?
Nightlife? None.
No partying?
Just sleep and crickets.
Gee, I was just wonderir,
because,
you know, I didn't want
to barge in on you today
unannounced.
I don't follow you.
No, last night I called
to tell ya that I was comir.
But there was no one at home.
[Woman On Police Radio,
Indistinct]
Uh, you a reporter?
Uh, no, uh...
Uh, Lieutenant, uh,
Columbo,
uh, police.
L.A. Unit.
All right.
L.A.P.D.
Yeah.
What brings you down here,
Lieutenant?
Well, I'm workir on a case.
Uh, listen,
this is not really my jurisdiction,
but do...
do ya mind if I browse around?
Well, help yourself, Lieutenant.
Always glad to cooperate.
[Reporter]
Didn't she have a bruise on her head?
[Man] How'd you know that, Ben?
Oh, come on, Sergeant.
Doc Webster told us.
All right, so there was a bruise.
Probably as a result of the boat capsizing
and rendering her unconscious.
Any indication the lady
was under the influence?
I can't ascertain that
until we see an autopsy report.
The doctor's
working on that right now.
[Reporter #1]
Sounds like drinkirto me.
[Reporter #2] Could she swim?
[Sergeant] How would I know
a thing like that?
I wasn't married to the lady.
[Reporter #3] Any living relatives?
I don't think so.
Somebody said she was a widow.
[Reporter #3]
How about the rowboat?
Rowboat? What about it?
Well, who'd it belong to?
Where'd it come from?
It belonged to the deceased.
I've got witnesses that have seen her
take it out on the lake.
[Voices Continue, Indistinct]
[Reporter #1]
Think she wanted
some fresh air last night?
[Sergeant]
This is all conjecture, gentlemen.
I mean, there's no way of telling.
Maybe she did.
Who knows?
It's also possible
that she had a heart seizure
or she got dizzy.
[Reporter #3]
Then you think it was an accident.
I certainly don't think it was foul play.
You gonna be in your office
this afternoon?
[Sergeant] Absolutely.
[Reporter #1]
How long was she in the water, Sergeant?
Oh, I don't know.
Wait'll we get the report.
We're startirto cover the same
old ground here, gentlemen.
Now, why don't you meet me
in my office an hour from now.
Well, we've got some
more questions here we'd like to...
I'll answer 'em all then.
I'll have the reports, and I'll be able
to give a lot more information. Okay?
Okay, Sarge, thank you.
[Columbo Reading]
- I still don't know what this means.
- It means that he knew her.
It means that he knew her
not casually, the way he said.
reasonably well.
All right.
You've got a romantic inscription
in a book and a champagne cork.
Now, what does that prove?
By itself,
it doesn't prove anything.
But once you assume
that Franklin committed these crimes,
everything fits together.
I just can't believe it.
I've known Ken too long.
He's not a murderer.
Mrs. Ferris, it wouldn't make a difference
if you knew him for a hundred years.
That wouldn't change anything.
This man, Franklin, took your husband's life!
Do you have a match?
Help yourself. I don't smoke.
It doesn't make sense, Lieutenant!
Ken has an alibi.
What's his motive?
I told ya how he could've
worked the phone.
Now, his motive
is the insurance money.
He needed cash.
He spent money like a drunken sailor.
He had two houses.
He's got paintings.
He's got women.
He's got...
What?
'Jack and Jill went up the hill.
'Did Jack killJill?
If so, find out why."
Jim. One of his story ideas.
Oh.
Lieutenant,
if Ken killed my husband,
then why did he murder
Miss La Sanka?
Well, it's my hunch
that she knew something.
Maybe she saw them together,
and she tried to blackmail him.
But that's pure guesswork, isn't it?
No, ma'am, it's not.
Not quite.
I checked the bank.
Yesterday, he took out $15,000.
Today, he put it back in again.
Now, why in the world
would he do that?
All right.
I'm still not convinced, but...
let's say I'll go along.
What happens now?
I don't know.
But I've got a pretty strong
circumstantial case.
It's just not enough.
If I had one piece of hard evidence,
I could nail this fella.
But you don't.
That's right, ma'am. I don't.
That's why I'm here.
Maybe
you can give it to me.
Me?
You knew both of these fellas very well.
I want you to tell me about 'em.
Anything. Just talk...
whatever comes into your mind.
Kind of like analysis
without the couch.
Would you like a little coffee first?
That'd be fine.
Okay.
I don't know
what you're looking for,
but here goes.
They met in a typewriter shop,
of all places.
Jim had broken a key,
and Ken needed a ribbon.
Does that help?
Yeah. Keep goir.
Well, I told you lot aboutJim.
[Faucet Running]
He was brilliant, really.
He'd wake up in the middle of the night
with ideas...always throwing off sparks.
I remember he even did it
on our honeymoon.
[Chuckles]
Funny thing is that Ken
didn't even talk about the books...
unless he was on television.
This the truck's gonna move my stuff
outta suite 803?
Yeah.
You almost finished?
Haven't started.
- What do you mean,
you haven't started?
- I'm only the driver, mister.
Ask the other two guys.
They've been in there a half an hour already.
Half hour?
[Bell Chimes]
[Door Opens, Closes]
Columbo!
Oh.
Hiya, Mr. Franklin.
Just finishing up
this last Melville mystery.
I didn't get a chance the other day.
All right.
Now, what are you doir here?
Why, I'm waiting for you.
I happened to be in the neighborhood.
You're always in the neighborhood!
Can you tell me what right you've got
to keep those movers out of this office?
Oh, listen, I'm sorry about that.
It's just...
You know what I thought?
I thought you and I should talk alone.
You and I have nothing to talk about.
Yes, we do, Mr. Franklin.
We have somethir to talk about.
I'm here to arrest ya
for the murder of your partner.
What?
Now, it's my duty to inform you
of your Constitutional rights...
Oh, will you cut that drivel?
I've written
that stuff so many times,
I know it by heart.
And what is this nonsense,
you're gonna arrest me?
Come on, Mr. Franklin.
Why don't you make a statement
and save us both a lot of trouble?
You know, I've really got ya.
All right, Lieutenant. You got me.
I'm your prisoner. Here.
Clamp the irons on me.
Do you wanna give me a dime first,
so I can phone my attorney?
Because I promise you, I'm gonna
sue you and your department...
for false arrest
and defamation of character.
I kinda knew it
right from the start.
It was nothing definite.
It was a lot of little things.
Little things...
driving back from San Diego
on the day of the murder
instead of taking a plane,
the open mail, never showing
any genuine emotion for a man
that you worked with for ten years...
[Laughs]
With that, you know
what they're gonna do?
They're gonna laugh you
right outta court.
But they're not gonna laugh
at the insurance policy, are they?
I've got a photostatic copy of it
here in my pocket.
They gonna laugh at the fact that you
withdrew $15,000, put it back the next day?
I've got the book that you gave
to Miss La Sanka with your signature in it.
You expect to get
a true bill of indictment
on that... trivia?
Come on, Lieutenant.
I was down in San Diego.
So was your partner.
That's a provocative statement.
Can you prove that?
Yes.
Not with the witness,
'cause you killed the witness.
But I got another way to prove it.
Well, you enlighten me.
I must say, I enjoy watching a man raise
without any cards in his hand.
You know what, Ken?
I'm gonna tell you the truth.
For a while there,
I never thought I was gonna get you.
Believe me,
you had me goir in such circles.
I couldn't figure it out.
Suddenly, I thought of something...
how clever that first murder was...
the phone gimmick,
working late in the office.
Brilliant.
Oh, are you awarding gold medals today?
Yes! For the first one,
not for the second one.
That was sloppy.
Mrs. Melville,
she'd have been very disappointed.
Oh, come on, get
to the climax, Lieutenant.
You're talking to a writer.
Am I?
That's not what I heard.
And that's the key:
That you're not a writer.
When Mrs. Ferris told me
that you didn't contribute to the writing,
that her husband did all the work,
That's a lie.
I had to say to myself,
'How could a man
with no talent for mysteries
make up such a clever murder?"
If you were that ingenious,
you'd be able to write your own books.
Go ahead. I'm fascinated,
as boring as it may be.
Then I got it.
The first one... the clever one...
that wasn't yours.
The second one...
the sloppy one... that was yours.
- But not the first.
- Oh?
And whose idea was that, then?
Your partner's. Had to be.
And his wife told me
how conscientious he was.
You know, the way he used to write down
his ideas on every odd scrap of paper,
backs of matches, whatever...
Ahh, ah. So that's why
you wouldn't let the movers in.
Well, I had to rummage around here
before they emptied everything out.
Is this
your partner's handwriting?
Well, I think I can prove it is.
Maybe I ought to read this to ya.
'Idea for a Melville book...
perfect alibi.
"A ' wants to kill 'B.'
Drives 'B ' to a remote house...
'and has him call his wife in city.
Tells her he's working late
at the office. Bang, bang."
Sound familiar?
That's the part you used,
practically word-for-word.
Should I read some more?
No.
[Door Opening, Closing]
Officer.
With this, I think I got
a conviction, don't you?
You got to admit I had you goir
for awhile though, didn't I?
Yes, you did.
[Snickers]
You wanna know the irony
of all of this?
That is my idea,
the only really good one
I ever had.
I must've told it toJim
over five years ago.
[Chuckles]
Whoever thought that idiot
would write it down?