This one is as crooked
as a dog's hind leg.
Fire it in the vice this afternoon.
Are those yesterday's
field reports?
Yes, sir.
I want them now.
[Teletype Clacking]
Three more units
added to security
at Coastal Aircraft.
No progress on
the Fairfax Insurance investigation.
We're working with their accountants
on the audit.
Uh, Brooks and Wilcox
are in court this morning
on the Monzio divorce.
Brooks anticipates no problem.
James case looking very positive...
no negative signs in sight.
All men on surveillance
have checked in except Russell,
but he's in Santa Barbara
and he's undercover.
Let me have the afternoon report
at 5:30.
Yes, sir.
I assume our guest has arrived.
Yes, sir, but Mr. Kennicutt
isn't hear yet.
Well, he's not due
for another 30 seconds.
He's just coming in now.
I want you to listen
very carefully, please.
My name is Arthur Kennicutt.
Mr. Brimmer's expecting me.
Oh, yes, sir.
Would you go right in, please?
Thank you.
Oh, Mr. Kennicutt.
You're right on time.
Won't you sit down?
Thank you.
Would you care
for something to drink?
Oh. Some coffee, black.
I was just reading
one of your papers.
I see you've taken a stand
on this federal judgeship
that's giving everybody fits.
I'd rather not talk politics right now,
Mr. Brimmer, if you don't mind.
Yes, of course.
Thank you, Henry.
Well, this is your wife's file,
Mr. Kennicutt,
and the fact sheet
shows five weeks now
of intensive surveillance.
All movement, personal contact,
telephone communications.
It's really quite extensive.
And?
Mr. Kennicutt,
you have nothing to worry about.
It's a clean bill of health.
- You sure?
- Well, I'm not in the habit
of making mistakes.
Yes. I'm sorry, of course.
But lately it's been like
waiting for a biopsy report...
benign or malignant.
Well, in this case, benign.
I don't know which I feel most,
relief or anger.
Anger?
At myself...
my idiotic suspicions.
But I suppose when one marries
a much younger woman,
one tends to become
a little paranoid.
[Brimmer]
Well, sometimes there's good cause.
In this case, not.
Read it at your leisure.
There's not a hint of another man.
You know, it's funny.
I love her.
I love her very much.
And I think I know her.
But lately I could have sworn that...
Well, it doesn't matter now.
I feel so guilty, I'm going to
start showering her with gifts.
She won't know what hit her.
Mr. Brimmer,
I owe you a great deal.
Well, it's a pleasure
to set your mind at rest, sir.
Thank you.
And you'll have my check
in the morning.
Very kind of you.
Thank you again.
Thank you.
Could you hear everything?
[Woman]
Yes.
- Well, you seem confused.
- Well, I don't know why
you asked me to come here.
- I thought it was obvious.
- No, not really.
- You...
- What you're trying to say
is that I lied to your husband.
Well, that's correct,
Mrs. Kennicutt.
I even went so far
as to falsify the report.
- Would you like a glass of water?
- No. Uh, nothing, thank you.
In point of fact,
you were having an affair.
The mars name was Archer.
It's over, Mr. Brimmer.
But I'm sure you already know that.
It was a mistake.
[Sighs]
A stupid mistake.
But I ended it.
And it won't ever happen again.
Why didn't you
tell my husband the truth?
[Sighs]
Oddly enough, Mrs. Kennicutt,
I am a moralist...
a vanishing species,
so I'm told.
A thousand broken marriages
come across my desk...
infidelities,
uh, domestic deceit.
In your case,
10 years of marriage...
and one brief indiscretion.
So, why not bend the truth
a little bit?
Uh, then you're
not going to tell him?
I haven't and I won't.
File's closed.
[Exhales Deeply]
[Sighs]
Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Brimmer.
I am so grateful.
How grateful?
Mrs. Kennicutt,
a detective agency
runs on information.
That's our raw material.
Your husband
owns three newspapers,
two on this coast
and one on the East.
Whenever anything happens
on the inside of business or politics
or even in the jet-set...
I still don't understand how I...
Information, Mrs. Kennicutt.
It is our only stock in trade.
For example,
at the moment I'm working on case...
wherein it would be
very beneficial to my client...
to have certain information
about a federal judge
that your husband is supporting.
Are you saying that you want me
to be a pipeline to my husband?
No. Just [Sighs]
A good listener.
Is it really asking so much,
Mrs. Kennicutt?
I can't do this kind of work alone.
I need that kind of help.
Why don't you think about it
and we'll talk again.
[Ice Cubes Jingling]
Your terrace door was unlocked,
so I trespassed.
Well, there's no car in the front.
Oh. I thought you knew everything,
Mr. Brimmer. We're neighbors.
My husband and I have a weekend house
about three miles from here.
Ironic, isn't it?
Why are you here?
Well, why else?
To discuss your...
What shall we call it?
Your proposition.
I've been walking on the beach
for hours, thinking.
And you've come to a decision.
Oh, yes.
Tell me something,
Mr. Brimmer.
How many other rich mers wives
owe you favors?
Do they all capitulate easily?
I'm waiting
for your answer.
Oh, indulge me.
I should think
the blackmail-ee
has some right.
Mrs. Kennicutt, I r...
The answer is no.
No deal.
Is that plain enough for you?
If you want a spy,
you find someone else.
All right.
I'll have to call your husband
in the morning and...
And what?
Tell him I had an affair?
Sorry. It won't work.
I'm going to tell him myself.
I can't believe
that you'd want to do that.
Well, what you believe
really doesn't matter, does it?
It's what Arthur thinks
that's important.
Maybe he'll ask for a divorce
or maybe he'll forgive me.
But it's time
I was honest with him.
You're being very foolish.
Only if I lose.
But you can't threaten me
anymore, can you?
You just lost your leverage.
Oh, and one other thing.
I'm also going to tell him
about the way you run your business.
I wouldn't advise that.
Oh, I'm sure you wouldn't.
Because whether he forgives me or not,
he's gonna despise you for lying to him.
And Arthur's not the right man
to have for an enemy.
Good night, Mr. Brimmer.
Mrs. Kennicutt,
I want you to reconsider.
Your husband
has some very powerful friends.
[Chortles]
That's right.
Now, if you'll please excuse me.
I cannot permit you to do that.
Well, you don't understand.
It's not your choice.
You let go of me!
Let go!
[Glass Shatters]
[Car Horn Blaring]
[Siren Approaching]
[Siren Dies Out]
[Engine Stops]
What's the trouble, Officer?
May I see your license
and registration?
Turn signal, right?
The right one.
You know, it's the second time
I got stopped today.
I tell you,
I'll get those things fixed
as soon as I can.
- You'll get 'em fixed now.
- I would, but I'm on my way
to a 187 P.C.
- Say, are you a cop?
- Uh, yeah, a lieutenant... Columbo.
Well, I'm sorry, Lieutenant,
I flagged you down.
Well, that's all right.
You're just doing your job.
Listen, I'll get those things fixed.
This license expires next week.
Oh. Oh, well, thanks.
Say, I better give you an escort.
That way you'll get where you wanna go.
Oh. Okay. Appreciate that.
But listen, not too fast.
[Police Radio Chatter]
Can't tell for sure,
but I don't think she was killed her.
Looks like the body was moved.
And the cause of death?
Probably a severe concussion.
Print team all wrapped up, Captain.
Nothing.
There were two blows.
Uh, send them on home.
Laceration on the cheek
and major contusion
at the base of the skull.
How do you read that?
It's hard to say.
Maybe somebody hit her
and she struck her head
going down.
- Lieutenant, you got that?
- I'll know more about this
after the autopsy.
Uh, yeah. Got a match?
Plus the approximate time of death.
No.
No tire tracks we can use.
Got a match?
I'm sorry. I don't smoke.
Oh.
No prints. Just smudges.
Money?
Just change. No currency.
You got a match.
No, I don't. Sorry.
Got a match.
Yeah, sure.
[Captain]
We're all finished here.
You can load it up.
Identification and purse.
Mrs. Arthur Kennicutt...
the Arthur Kennicutt.
How do you know that?
Credit card's made out
to Kennicutt Publications.
What's the problem?
Newspapers.
If we don't handle this
according to Kennicutt's
satisfaction,
he's got an awful lot of front pages
to beat us over the head with.
Thought I told you
to move that out of here.
Lieutenant,
what are you looking at?
The bruise, sir.
The lady has a bruise
on the left cheek.
We know that.
I knew
you werert listening.
[Police Radio Chatter Continues]
It's Lenore.
I wanna get out of here.
Oh. Thank you, Lieutenant.
Would you like to be alone
for a few moments?
No, no. I can feel sorry for myself
some other time,
after you've caught him.
Well, should we get down
to business?
Are you sure
there's nothing else you want?
As the husband,
I'm the most likely suspect, correct?
Uh...
You don't have to worry
about my feelings, Lieutenant.
She was killed last night.
What time?
Between 8:00 and 9:00.
Well, I was in San Francisco
addressing a conference.
I didn't fly back
until this morning.
Uh, you have
the flight numbers on that?
My secretary can give them to you,
together with my hotel
and my schedule.
You'll check them all out, naturally.
Yes, sir.
And when you do,
you'll dismiss me as a possibility...
and then get down to the real business
of finding the real killer.
And I want him found, Lieutenant.
Soon.
I'll do my best.
I'm sure you will.
Uh, Mr. Kennicutt, it would help
if you could tell us a few things.
Did your wife
have any enemies?
Lenore never offended a soul.
She was an extraordinary woman.
I see. This question is a bit awkward,
but I'm afraid I'm gonna have to ask it...
was there ever, uh,
another man in her life?
Naturally. More than one.
But that was years ago,
before we were married.
- No, sir.
I meant since you were married.
- You're speaking of an affair?
Well, I'm afraid we're gonna
have to consider it.
Well, don't bother.
Lenore was faithful to me in every way.
She had a clean bill of health.
All right. Clean bill of health.
So you don't think
we ought to go in that direction?
No, I don't.
All right.
Can you tell us about her habits?
What did she do in her spare time?
Nothing unusual.
Shopping, charity work.
Sports.
Sports. What kind of sports
did she play?
Oh, tennis. She was also
very fond of skin diving.
Yes. Uh, did she do this with you, sir?
Did she do it with friends?
With friends, Lieutenant.
Female friends,
in case you're wondering.
Female friends.
All right, sir.
I think I've got enough to start with.
Thank you very much.
Lieutenant,
I want you
to understand something.
I married a woman
young enough to be my daughter.
A lot of people were skeptical,
but it worked for us.
We loved each other.
We loved each other very much.
We even thought of having a child.
I want this man caught.
And I must warn you,
I don't intend to be patient.
Yes, sir.
Oh, Lieutenant.
Thanks for the coffee.
You're welcome, sir.
Good morning, Lieutenant.
Good morning, sir.
Would you like some coffee,
some juice?
Uh, nothing for me.
No. Thank you very much.
Any progress?
Uh, no, sir.
I hate to admit this,
but, uh, nothing.
Not a single lead?
No, sir. Nothing.
Well, uh... Well,
some of my associates think...
that, uh, your wife was mugged
and the fella ran away with the money.
But, um, you see,
they can't really explain
how the body was moved.
And, uh, now, me, I don't know.
I, uh... I think
she knew the murderer.
Why? Excuse me.
[Ringing]
Yes.
Yes?
All right. Be right in.
Why?
Well, her behavior seems
a little strange, sir.
Uh, she went out to the beach house
in the middle of the week,
which is unusual.
And, uh, she said to the caretaker
she had some thinking to do...
and then she went for a walk.
And then the next morning her body
was found on the other side of town.
What are you getting at?
I wish I knew.
I don't know.
It's just that it sounds to me
like a woman that has a problem.
Now, did your wife
have any personal problems?
My wife was a very happy woman.
Uh-huh. Yeah, well,
it's just that
if she did have a problem,
I thought that maybe it would be
connected with the murder.
But you've no proof of that.
Oh, no, sir. No.
Lieutenant, I call the City Room
every half hour to find out
what you people are doing.
So far, not a word.
No arrest...
not even a promise of one.
Now you tell me
you haven't a lead.
Well, I'm sorry, Mr. Kennicutt.
Uh, looks like it's gonna be slow.
It doesn't have to be.
Lieutenant.
Lieutenant Columbo,
this is Mr. Brimmer.
How do you do?
Lieutenant.
You've heard of
Brimmer Associates?
Uh, no, I haven't.
Well, it's security
and investigations,
Lieutenant.
You might say you and I
are in the same business.
Oh, really?
Matter of fact,
I was talking about you just last night.
I ran into the commissioner
at a party.
He speaks
very highly of you.
Naturally, you're wondering
why Mr. Brimmer's here.
Now, please don't take this
as a reflection on you,
but I've engaged his firm
to work on the case.
Well, now, Arthur,
I'm here in an advisory capacity...
a supplemental capacity only.
I don't want
the lieutenant to get the idea
that I'm competing with him.
Uh, but there's no reason
why a private agency
and a public one...
can't cooperate,
is there?
No.
You see,
I want as much coverage
in this case as possible.
And when Mr. Brimmer called
and offered his services,
I thought it was an excellent idea.
Sure, uh,
I can understand that.
Uh, you two know
each other?
Well, Mr. Brimmer's done
some work for me.
I see. I see.
[Clears Throat]
Some kind of security work?
Guards for the paper?
Oh, it was a personal matter.
The point is, Lieutenant,
I told Arthur on the phone
I couldn't imagine you wouldn't
accept a helping hand...
considering the manpower shortage
in your department.
You see, Mr. Brimmer
used to be a police officer himself.
[Brimmer]
Well, it was a long time ago.
But at least I can understand
your problems, Lieutenant.
Well, now, listen,
I said to Mr. Kennicutt I'm grateful
for all the help I can get.
I'm just not sure
how my superior's gonna take this.
That's already been taken care of.
It's just that Mr. Kennicutt is anxious
for a quick resolution to the case.
You can understand that.
Well, naturally.
[Brimmer]
Well, good.
I hope the association
will be beneficial to you.
Oh, I'm sure it will. Yeah.
You know, I suddenly feel
very much more optimistic
about this whole thing.
Uh, it's not based on anything,
no facts, but,
you know,
I'm a superstitious guy.
You know, I believe in signs.
I believe in palmistry and astrology
and all that kinda thing.
You don't, I know that.
Oh, definitely not.
Let me see your hand.
You see, Mr. Kennicutt,
that's your fate line
and it breaks there.
That was your bad fortune.
But it picks up again,
and that's interesting.
That's a very good omen.
May I?
Mmm.
Deep line of Apollo.
That's a man devoted to his work.
Your Apollo line
crosses the mound of the Moon.
You know, that's very rare.
And very impressive.
That's the sign of a man
who's destined to attain
a very particular kind of distinction.
That's a very good sign.
I know you think it's silly,
but I'm gonna make a believer
out of you before I'm done.
It was very nice meeting you.
Nice to have met you.
Bye-bye.
Oh, Mr. Brimmer.
Large thumb, low mound of Venus.
That means ambition,
purposefulness.
That's a closet, Lieutenant.
[Chuckles]
Oh, gee. I'm sorry.
A lot of people
make the same mistake.
Say, that's a terrific-looking
set of clubs. Do you mind?
Go ahead.
These seem light.
Are these ladies' clubs?
- They were Lenore's.
- You didn't say she played golf,
did you?
You mentioned tennis
and skin diving.
- That's because she just started.
- Ahh. I see. Where'd she play?
At the country club.
I see. At the club.
Well, I was just wondering
why shejust didn't keep her clubs
in the locker room?
She did.
That's an extra set
she used to take lessons with.
Oh, I see.
Well, that explains it. Right.
Uh, you mean
she didn't take lessons at her own club?
She took them someplace else?
Sky Lane.
Why, is it important?
It's not important. It's just I like to
get that background information
very precise if I can.
Bye.
- Is this the right door?
- [Chuckles] Yes.
Well, what was that
all about?
Well, I think, uh, police techniques
have changed a little over the years.
Here, try it again.
And remember, keep the back
of your left hand straight.
None of this.
Just stroke it easy, all right?
Oh, that was good.
You're getting better.
Well, I still don't think
I'm ever gonna learn this game.
Oh, you just have to
keep your eye on the ball,
watch your concentration.
You're coming along fine.
Do we have time
for another bucket?
Sorry, Jenny. Time's up.
Tomorrow, 3:00.
Tomorrow then.
You a member of the club?
Uh, no. No, I'm,
uh, Lieutenant Columbo.
I'm from the police.
[Mumbles]
What's the problem?
I'd like to ask you a few questions
about a Lenore Kennicutt.
Uh, you knew her?
Not very well.
I gave her a few lessons.
I see. Uh, well, this is
your appointment book, isn't it?
Well, you should know.
You've been looking at it.
Well, no offense.
I was just killing time.
But, uh, you know,
now that you mention it,
I see that you gave her
a lot of lessons.
She liked the game.
I see.
Well, look here's the thing.
Um, since you spent a lot of time
with her,
I was wondering if you could
give me some help.
How?
Was she the type of woman...
now this is just between
you and me...
was she the type of woman
who was on the lookout?
I mean, did you ever notice her
give her eye to any of the men
around here?
Uh, look, Lieutenant.
We better get one thing straight.
I teach them golf
and I play in their tournaments,
but I don't get involved
in their personal lives.
If they wanna pair off,
that's none of my business.
Okay. All right.
Uh, well, thanks a lot.
It's quite all right.
Take it easy.
Uh, say, uh,
what kind of club is this?
Oh, that's a number one wood.
Number one wood.
Listen, uh, could you
give me a lesson?
What?
No, I'm serious.
You know what my trouble is?
I work too hard.
Never out of the office.
I figure this:
If I could take up a sport,
get out in the fresh air
and get some exercise,
that'd do me some good.
- What do you say?
- Well, I...
Just for a few minutes.
Just to, you know, start to swing.
Come on.
Say, you know what was a funny thing
about your appointments
with Mrs. Kennicutt?
Uh, the first two
were in the morning...
and all the rest,
and I counted 13 of them,
uh, they were always in the middle
or the late afternoon.
So?
Uh, well,
I guess it's not important.
I guess it's nothing.
Uh, wait a minute.
I'll take off my coat.
Except that, uh,
now, every time
you had an appointment
with Mrs. Kennicutt,
it was always
the last lesson of the day.
I like to finish
at a reasonable hour.
Doesn't everyone?
Oh, I see.
So those days, you left the club.
I thought maybe you'd hang around to
see if you could pick up an odd lesson.
Well, I didn't always go home.
Oh, who said anything
about going home?
Oh. What I mean is I didn't always
leave the club. Sometimes...
Hey, listen.
Can I help you out?
Don't say anything else.
You don't have an attorney.
Wait until you get an attorney.
This way you can hurt your case.
Believe me,
I know something about my business.
I don't know nothing about golf,
you know. See that's your business.
I know something about my business.
And believe me, you know,
down through the years, uh,
you get so that you develop
a nose for things, you see?
And, uh...
After a while, the old nose
just tells you when someone's
not giving you the truth.
Now, uh,
I'm gonna forget about the lesson,
'cause I could never learn this game,
but I'll be back to talk to you.
Ground covered by the police
is not our concern.
One thing to bear in mind,
money was taken.
Granted, it could have
been a smoke screen,
but sometimes the obvious answer
is the correct one.
Now, Brooks...
Yes, sir?
Check into her banking account
with particular attention to withdrawals.
See if you can find out how much cash
she was carrying that day.
Mr. Kennicutt will be glad to cooperate.
Now, my theory, gentlemen,
and you will gear your efforts
in this direction,
Mrs. Kennicutt was walking
along the Pacific Coast Highway.
She was forced into a car...
by someone.
The motive was robbery.
She probably fought back.
In any case, she was killed.
The murderer drove around
in a panic...
and finally all the way out to here,
where he got rid of the body.
[Intercom Buzzer]
Yes?
[Woman]
Lieutenant Columbo to see you.
Who?
Oh, yes.
Yes, send him in.
Gentlemen, we'll finish this later.
I'll call you. Thank you.
Lieutenant!
Come in!
Whew! Boy.
This is quite a building.
This all yours?
'Fraid so.
Must be a lot of business
for your kinda company these days.
Well, we can't handle it all.
Sit down.
Uh, listen, your secretary called.
She said you wanted to see the files
on the case, so I thought it'd be a lot
safer if I brought 'em over myself.
Oh. That's very nice of you.
It wasn't necessary,
but I appreciate it very much.
Uh, want some coffee?
No. No, thanks.
Thank you.
Uh, those are the duplicates.
Okay.
Yes, this will help.
A lot of it. I wonder if you can
give me a little rundown.
Well, it's just what I told
Mr. Kennicutt.
No leads. Except, you know,
I was looking through that stuff
last night.
Mm-hmm.
And, uh, drives my wife crazy,
you know.
Because we have the lamp
right next to the bed,
and the poor thing, she can't sleep.
Did you find anything?
No, not really. Well, uh,
take the autopsy report.
Yes. Here it is.
You see now,
that jibed with something
that I noticed about the body...
the first time I saw it,
and that bothered me.
Mrs. Kennicutt
was struck on the left cheek,
and she had a bruise.
And she had a weird kinda cut.
Um...
Do you see what I mean?
Um, no. I don't think so.
Well, let's start with the cut,
because that's what bothered me.
I said to myself,
'Now what in the world
could have caused that kind of cut?"
Uh, does this lighter work?
Yeah, I think so.
Uh...
Uh, wh... where was I?
About the cut.
Oh, yes.
What could have caused the cut?
I said to myself, ' It could be a ring."
A ring of... You mean a finger ring.
This kind of ring.
Yeah, something like that.
Now here's the way I figured it.
Suppose you were gonna
strike somebody.
Suppose it was a woman.
Now, do you punch her?
Well, maybe.
But more than likely,
you hit with your open hand.
Either this way or this way.
Mm-hmm.
Now, if you hit this way,
then the ring is not gonna
cause any cut.
So I figured it was
a backhand blow like this.
All right?
I still don't follow you too well,
because that would, uh,
that would put it over on...
But I used my right hand,
you see?
Yeah.
And if the ring was on the right hand,
then the bruise would be
on the right cheek.
But it was on the left cheek,
so the murderer was left-handed.
Struck her like this.
Which means
the murderer is left-handed.
Well, that's interesting.
That's provided, of course,
all these, uh, speculations are valid.
Yeah, I would say that
we have a left-handed murderer,
and, uh,
and an unpremeditated crime.
We have?
Oh, I think so, yes.
I mean, I don't think
a man kills with his hands
unless he's angry.
As a matter of fact, you know,
maybe he didn't mean to do it.
Could be.
You know,
maybe it was an accident.
You know, I got a feeling
that when we find our friend,
it's gonna turn out
that he has a terrible temper.
Hmm.
[Chuckles]
Well, maybe you're right.
I certainly wish I had your crystal ball,
Lieutenant.
Why don't you let me
digest this material,
and then we'll talk again.
Okay. All right. Fine.
Sure. Listen.
I want to thank you
for the time.
Listen. Thank you.
Right.
Oh, listen,
before I forget, uh...
Gee whiz.
I didn't wanna forget that.
But, uh, let's see.
I had a receipt here
that I wanted you to sign.
Well, listen,
let's just make one up.
It's a receipt
for the files.
Isn't that weird?
- What a coincidence.
- What's that?
Here, a moment ago, we were
talking about left-handed people,
and you're left-handed.
And right-handed.
I'm ambidextrous.
That means I don't favor
either hand particularly.
It's a character trait shared
by about 10% of the world's population.
Ten percent?
No kidding?
Anything else?
Uh, no.
No, I don't think so. Uh, oh, listen.
This is a little bit off the subject.
My sister-in-law, she wants to
buy a place out at the beach.
How do you like it out there?
Who told you I was living
out at the beach?
Well, no one.
L... I noticed your car
out in front of Mr. Kennicutt's.
You know, you parked it there
in the driveway.
As I was walking by,
I saw the chrome was tarnished.
You know what the salt air does to it.
It just eats the life out of it.
Yeah, that part's a problem, all right.
Uh, you're a very observant man,
Lieutenant.
That's not what my wife says.
[Laughs]
Well, you tell your sister-in-law
that she will love it at the beach...
if she doesn't mind that problem
with the salt air on the chrome.
I'll give her that message.
And thanks again.
Thank you.
Oh, uh, say.
Have you ever been
in Mr. Kennicutt's house?
Yes, I met you there.
No, I didn't mean the big house.
I meant out at the beach.
I was just wondering, because
your beach house and his beach house,
they're fairly close, aren't they?
No. It's a couple miles.
That close?
Tsk. Isn't that a coincidence?
[Chuckles]
I'll tell you,
this case is just full of'em.
[Door Closes]
[Sighs]
Why don't you and I take a walk?
When you showed up today,
I... I kinda panicked.
Then you did have
an affair with her?
Turning on the ladies
is about the only thing
I do well.
I'm not a very good golfer.
Yeah, go on.
Well, it was pretty good
for a while...
at least for me.
She got the guilts.
Funny thing, I think
she really loved her husband.
One day she said,
'Ken, this is bad for both of us.
Let's call it off." So we did.
Must have shook you up
when we found her dead.
I couldn't believe it.
Then I got to thinking,
sooner or later, you guys
would find out about me.
Maybe even think
I killed her.
The night she died, I was...
I was home watching the tube.
No calls. No company.
No alibi. That's...
That's why I started to run.
Uh-huh.
I can understand that.
You didn't kill her.
No, no.
I know that, but this afternoon,
you gave me the impression...
No. You're in the clear.
You got nothing to worry about.
You see, whoever did this,
he had to wear a ring.
Now, you don't wear a ring.
Well, I could have taken it off.
No, not with that tan,
because that would show.
Now listen.
Tell me something.
Mrs. Kennicutt...
Did Mrs. Kennicutt
ever indicate to you...
that she was concerned
that her husband knew
about you two?
No.
That's funny that you
mention it though,
because, well,
I was concerned.
Why?
Well, Lenore never saw anyone,
but I'm sure we were being followed.
By who?
Well, there was
this one guy in particular.
Sharp, well-dressed.
I only caught him in flashes, but...
Well, he... he had a crew cut.
Kind of an ex-marine type.
[Telephone Ringing]
- Yes?
- Wilcox, Mr. Brimmer.
The subject is meeting with Archer,
and they've engaged in conversation.
Did you overhear anything?
No, sir. But Archer seems to
be doing most of the talking.
Maintain the surveillance
and report to me in the morning.
Yes, sir.
[Phone Ringing]
Why, you little bum, you.
Hello?
Oh, yes, he is. Leo.
Mr. Brimmer.
- Yes, sir?
- I'm sorry to trouble you at home, Leo.
No sweat.
Just playing with Teddy.
Well, I've got a little something
I want you to do for me. It may
complicate your life a little bit.
- When?
- Immediately.
- Set it up through my secretary.
- Yes, sir. I'll be in touch.
Every one of our operatives
is a skilled marksman.
Actually, our policy
is to avoid the use of the weapon.
This is our memory bank,
Lieutenant.
Millions ofbits
of information,
all cross-filed and on tape,
immediately available.
There are more electrical impulses
in this room than in your brain.
Hard to believe.
[Chuckles]
We here at Brimmer Associates
use the most up-to-date equipment.
Years ahead of what you use
at police headquarters.
Company cars...
custom designed for us.
Most of them with telephonic
or radio communication.
Phew! It's very impressive.
Oh, uh, just one moment,
Lieutenant.
One other thing
that might interest you.
If you'll just move
past this gate.
- It's not working.
- Well, it has to be.
You're carrying a gun,
aren't you, Lieutenant?
No.
No? Oh.
Well, that explains
the malfunction.
Look here. A special system
is built into the gate.
Now, if you had a gun,
it would have registered.
It's just like out at the airport.
It's a security precaution.
Not that we expect our clients
to be carrying concealed weapons,
but, uh,
well, there have been
a few exceptions.
Really?
Well, a guy came in here
just about a month ago.
Harmless looking.
An accountant
for Mid-Century Oil.
We were doing
a company audit.
[Brimmer] Mr. Denning?
I asked you to show
the lieutenant around.
I did not suggest that you discuss
our confidential matters...
with anyone at anytime!
Our clients pay us to be discreet.
Yes, sir.
Won't you come in, Lieutenant?
Sorry about the outburst,
but my people have got to learn.
This is a business of trust.
I can't have them gossiping
about the clients.
Thank you, Henry.
Hope you'll have lunch with me.
Like quenelle of sole?
Uh, well, if it's fish,
I like fish. I love fish.
Yeah, it's fish.
Drop your coat and dig in.
On the Kennicutt case,
my men have come up
with an interesting lead.
There were two derelicts
seen in the area.
I have their description.
I sent them over to your office,
copies.
Right.
Uh, I'll have that checked out.
Anything new on your end?
Uh, oh, yeah.
Yeah, we got a couple of things.
It seems as though Mrs. Kennicutt
was having an affair, you see?
Uh...
Boy, this is delicious.
How do you make this stuff?
I'll have a recipe sent over to you.
You were saying?
Oh, yeah.
Uh, it seems as though...
Mrs. Kennicutt, uh,
she was having an affair.
And, uh...
Oh?
Oh, listen, when you send the recipe,
would you send it to the house?
- Don't send it to the office.
- Yes, I'll send it to your house.
Yeah, she was having an affair
with some golf pro at some country club.
And, uh, here's
the interesting thing.
Not only
were they having an affair,
but it seems as though
they were being watched.
Now I got this nutty notion.
Suppose Mr. Kennicutt, uh...
I'll tell you, it's too far-fetched.
Sometimes it helps to test it out.
Try me.
It's really crazy. Well, listen.
It doesn't cost anything.
Suppose...
Suppose Mr. Kennicutt...
hired somebody
to check up on his wife.
And this somebody
lied to him.
He said to Mr. Kennicutt, ' Look.
Your wife,
she's got a clean bill of health."
Now this somebody,
whoever it is,
he's in a perfect position
to blackmail Mrs. Kennicutt.
Now suppose she refuses.
See? She says,
'No, I'm gonna go tell my husband."
Hmm.
I think it's a terrific motive,
don't you?
Lieutenant, you have
a marvelously convoluted mind.
I do?
I like it.
The trouble with your theory is,
not only is it very tenuous,
but it's impossible to prove,
isn't it?
I, uh... Oh.
Got a little tomato on that there.
Well, I said it was nutty.
What do you think?
You think I oughta drop it, hmm?
[Clears Throat]
If you believe in it, stick to it.
Run it on down.
One other thing
you should keep in mind.
Nothing at all to do with the case.
- What's that?
- Your future.
I'd like you to work
for Brimmer Associates.
Me?
That's why I had you taken
on a V.I.P. Tour.
We're a growing organization.
You can see that.
You'll be a valuable piece
of manpower for us.
Oh, boy. You really know
how to toss a curve.
No, no, I don't mean it that way.
I'm quite serious.
You're a good man, Columbo...
up here.
It's time you were thinking
about advancement.
What does
a lieutenant make?
If you come with us,
I'm almost positive
I can triple your yearly income.
Whew! Boy.
I'll tell you, it's all so sudden.
Uh, let me talk it over with my wife.
Of course talk it over with your wife.
Think about it carefully.
But remember,
we want you here.
Listen. I'm very flattered.
I mean that.
Just let me mull it over a little bit.
Well, while you're mulling,
consider my career.
If I'd stayed with the force,
by now,
probably with luck,
I could have been
a captain of detectives.
Hmm?
With one eye on the promotion list,
and the other eye on my car payments.
No house by the ocean.
No freedom to travel.
No... what would you say?
Power or sense of accomplishment.
Have I succeeded
in getting through...
[Clears Throat]
In stimulating you?
Definitely. Yes, sir.
Yes, I'm gonna give it all
a lot of thought.
That's as much as I can ask.
Uh, one thing.
Hmm?
If I came with you, would I still
be working on the Kennicutt case?
Well, let's see.
I have men who are perfectly capable
of handling the Kennicutt case.
No. I have several other matters
that are far more important than that
I'd like to put you on right away.
Lieutenant,
to the knock of opportunity.
Hey.
Hi.
Dry throat for some reason.
Oh, help yourself.
Yeah. Hey, I hope I didn't
get you into trouble before.
I mean, I'm sorry
about what happened.
I'm used to it.
Why? Does he blow off
a lot of steam?
Well, let's just say
our founding father
has quite a temper.
No kidding.
That's funny, because he...
he looks to me like he's a guy
that's always under control.
Uh, correction.
He's under control
most of the time.
And when people
like that let go,
stand back.
Oh. I'll tell you
why I'm interested.
He offered me a job.
Oh?
Yeah.
Well, welcome to the family.
Yeah, here's my problem.
I don't know
how much to ask for.
Whatever you can get.
Top man can pull down about 30,000.
No kidding? [Whistles]
That's a lot of money.
Gee, listen.
Does anybody else here
make more than that?
I mean,
besides Mr. Brimmer?
Well, maybe Leo.
Who's Leo?
Leo Gentry.
He's the boy who gets
the cream of the cases.
Hey, I think I know him.
Crew cut, ex-marine type?
Yeah, that's Leo.
Teacher's pet,
at least this month.
Hey, listen.
Where can I talk to him?
Maybe he can give me
a few pointers.
Oh. I haven't seen him
around yet today, but, uh...
I'll get his address
from Personnel.
Uh, don't mention it
to Brimmer.
Who me? No.
That's the last thing I'd do.
[Children Chattering]
Higher.
Higher? Listen.
If you go any higher,
you're gonna go
right over the top.
Hey, what's going on?
Mrs. Gentry? I wanna tell you,
you got a terrific kid here.
Nothing frightens him.
You can't scare this boy.
I said higher!
Higher?
All right, listen. You go higher,
and I'll eat your ice cream, all right?
No, I wanna eat it.
You wanna eat it.
All right. Here you go.
You're coming down.
Down to earth. There you are.
Get your ice cream.
Do we know each other?
Uh, no.
Uh, my name is Columbo.
I'm a lieutenant.
I'm from the police.
My daddy's a private eye.
I know that, Teddy.
And he's a very good one.
Listen. Do you mind
if I ask you a few questions?
- Well, is it about Leo's work?
- Well, not exactly.
I'm working on a case, and I thought
maybe he could help me out.
- But I can't seem to locate him.
- He went away.
That's right, Lieutenant.
His boss called last night...
and sent him
on a special assignment.
Oh, I see.
Uh, do you know where he went?
Or, uh, how long
he's gonna be away?
Sorry. That's the way
it is with Leo.
He took his passport,
so I guess he's overseas
somewhere.
I see.
Is there
something wrong?
No, no, no. No, not really.
Listen. Maybe you could help me out.
Was Leo recently on a case
where he was following a woman?
A married woman?
Well, it's... it's possible,
but I don't really know.
No? You never discuss Leo's work?
No. It's a household rule.
I mean,
I'm not very much
at keeping secrets.
If Leo were to tell me anything,
it'd be all over the Laundromat.
If you have any questions,
you better ask Leo.
It's kinda hard to ask him,
because I can't locate him.
He went away.
But why don't you talk
to his boss, Mr. Brimmer?
He can tell you
what Leo's working on.
Uh, oh, yeah.
I, uh... Thanks.
I have the feeling
he won't be too much help.
But, uh, at any rate,
uh, I'm sorry I bothered you.
Bye-bye, Teddy.
F- E-L-O-P-
Z-D.
All right. Now try
the next to the bottom line.
F-D-P-
T-C-E-O?
Perfect vision.
Well, it should be.
This is a new prescription.
Here's your temporary.
You should have your license
in a few weeks.
Thank you very much.
Keep this too.
Next.
Now, while I mark your test,
please read from the eye chart,
third line down.
Did that lady say that
she just got a new pair of glasses?
- What?
- [Slams Counter]
- She wasn't wearing glasses.
- Of course she was.
Excuse me.
Uh, wait.
What about the eye chart?
And all of a sudden,
I remembered this picture.
See? She's wearing glasses.
But there were no glasses
on the body.
Now, could she have
dropped them somewhere?
I'm sorry, Lieutenant,
but you're on the wrong track.
Why?
Well, shortly after
that picture was taken,
Lenore gave up
wearing glasses.
She switched
to contact lenses.
Ah, contact lenses.
Just a matter of vanity.
She thought she looked better.
Uh-huh.
Did she wear 'em often?
All the time.
She was extremely nearsighted.
Mr. Kennicutt,
where's your wife's
personal effects?
The funeral director
sent them over.
I've avoided
going through them.
Do you mind?
No, go ahead.
This her lens case?
Yes.
It's empty.
Well, she was probably
wearing them when she died.
Well, then maybe, uh...
Maybe what?
Mr. Kennicutt,
I'm gonna ask your permission
for something.
This is the world's
biggest long shot.
And it's gonna be
painful for you.
But I think it's won'th a try.
Would it help?
There are no guarantees.
All right, Lieutenant.
You have a blank check.
Mobile Operator,
the number I want
is 476-7301.
[Line Ringing]
They just arrived,
and they're entering the vault.
The medical examiner's
with them.
Why? What's the reason?
Haven't been able to find out, sir,
but I did learn one thing.
Kennicutt signed
an exhumation order.
All right, stay there.
I'll be right over.
Get my car ready.
He says it won't take long.
[Car Ignition Grinding]
[Ignition Continues Grinding]
What's the trouble?
I don't know, sir.
The battery's okay,
but the car won't start.
[Ignition Grinding]
I'm in a hurry.
Get me another car.
Yes, sir.
Have this one serviced.
Tell them I want it tomorrow.
Yes, sir.
[Tires Squealing]
[Police Radio Chatter]
[Police Radio Chatter Continues]
Arthur.
I should have phoned you,
but there wasn't time.
Well, it's all right.
One of my men told me
you were here.
Something break?
I don't know yet.
They're exhuming Lenore's body.
Tell me why.
Well, the lieutenant's
working on a long shot.
Apparently, she was wearing
her contact lenses when she was killed.
How's that significant?
Well, there's a chance that
she might have lost one of them...
maybe both of them
at the scene of the crime.
Well, Arthur,
I don't like to be critical,
but that's more
than a long shot.
You might as well buy
a lottery ticket.
Maybe not.
Listen to me.
My nephew wears those things,
and half of the time they're falling out.
Now, the other morning at breakfast,
one of them ended up in the cereal.
[Brimmer] Mrs. Kennicutt
is not your nephew, Lieutenant.
Listen. Mrs. Kennicutt was struck forcibly.
Now let's bear that in mind.
Why isn't it possible
that they were knocked loose?
Anything's possible.
The autopsy report
said nothing about
any of this at all.
Listen. Forget about
the autopsy report. I checked with
the medical examiner about that.
They snuffed it off.
They didn't even bother to look.
All they were concerned about
was the cause of death.
[Man]
Lieutenant.
Well, I hope it's not a waste.
What else can I do?
I've got to pursue
every possibility.
Arthur, it's almost
a criminal breach...
to disappoint you now
after what you've been through.
Move over.
Listen. We're in luck.
The right contact lens is missing,
and it's not in the coffin.
Well, it might have fallen out
in the morgue, I guess.
Or in the ambulance. Or in the street.
She might have lost it
before she was killed.
Could be a hundred places.
That's true, but maybe...
and this is what
we gotta hope for...
maybe it's at the place
where she was murdered.
[Kennicutt]
But we don't know
where that place is.
[Columbo]
No, sir, we don't.
We don't know for sure.
But I've got a few hunches.
Unless you can be specific,
I can't help.
I think the lieutenant
deserves some room.
Don't you?
As you wish.
You go your own way,
Lieutenant.
Thank you, sir. I will.
But keep us posted.
Yes, sir. I will.
I'll keep you posted.
[Sighs]
I only wish one thing.
I wish the murderer
knew about this.
Why?
There'd be a piece of conclusive evidence
that might be lying around in his premises,
and he'd have to find it
before we did.
I'll keep you posted, sir.
[Doorbell Rings]
Oh, uh, Mr. Brimmer.
Lieutenant.
Listen. I'm sorry
to bother you at this hour,
but, uh... May I come in?
Yes, sure. Come on in.
There's something
I wanted to talk to you about.
Okay. Fine,
if you can make it a little brief.
It's been a late day.
Oh, sure. Say, this is
some terrific place you got here.
And you got the sound
of the ocean all the time, huh?
Yeah.
Well, me, I love the beach.
I love it.
Except when the water gets cold,
then I don't like to go in.
Then I like a pool.
Lieutenant, did you say you
had something on your mind?
Oh, yeah.
It's about that job you offered me.
I've been giving it a lot of thought.
Uh, as a matter of fact,
uh, I haven't been able to sleep.
And, uh...
Boy, this is a fantastic rug.
My wife would love this rug.
We gotta get a new rug,
and this is just the kind she wants.
Fantastic piling, huh?
Very soft.
Bet you could lose a shoe in here
for a week, you wouldn't find it.
It's late.
I still got a lot of work to do.
You were talking about my job offer.
I really don't think I'd be very happy
making a change, you know.
I like it where I am.
It's not a bad life.
Mm-hmm. Okay.
Uh, is that final?
I think so, yes.
No hard feelings?
No, no, certainly not.
I just, uh...
Well, I think you're
making a mistake.
That's all.
You're probably right.
You know, my wife,
she's always said
I don't have enough ambition.
You know what it was
that really made up my mind?
What was that?
The Kennicutt case.
I don't wanna give up
working on it just now.
Not when I'm so close
to a solution.
Well, uh, are you gonna
let me in on it?
Oh, certainly.
Don't worry.
You'll be the first to know.
Good night.
[Car Door Closes]
[Engine Starts]
[Vehicle Departs]
- Hello?
- Yes, this is Mr. Brimmer.
You took my car in
to be repaired, didn't you?
Yes, sir. Just like you said.
They'll try to have it for you
as soon as they can.
All right then.
Good night.
[Footsteps]
[Keys Jingling]
[Car Door Opens, Closes]
You mind telling us
what you're doing?
I'd say that was none of
your business, Lieutenant.
Well, if you say so,
but, uh, it's gonna be kinda
hard to explain, isn't it?
I mean, breaking and entering?
That's against the law.
Checking the trunk of your car.
What in the world
were you looking for?
Papers... for a case.
I thought they were here.
It's an emergency.
Why don't you admit it?
You were searching the trunk,
'cause that's where you hid the body.
All right.
What's the next step?
Why don't we go downtown
and talk it over?
Am I under arrest?
I guess you could say so.
On what evidence?
I think it's gotta be
more comfortable downtown.
All right.
Let's get this farce
over with.
Grab his arm!
It was an accident, Arthur.
It wasn't... premeditated.
I hardly knew your wife.
I didn't want to hurt
either one of you.
It happened.
How'd you get it?
I got it from
the cut on her cheek
and your ring.
You never should have
let me read your palm.
'Cause then I felt the ring
and I felt the two diamonds
sticking out...
and that raised
rectangular border.
That matched up
with the cut on her cheek.
You should have
taken that job.
You know,
we're lucky Lenore lost this.
Uh, she didn't lose it.
What?
When I spoke
to the medical examiner
at the cemetery,
he told me
that both contact lenses
were on the body.
But that's impossible.
If it isn't hers, whose was it?
Who knows?
Anyway, it doesn't make any difference.
The fact that it's not
the real contact lens,
that doesn't count.
What does count
is Mr. Brimmer's actions...
coming here tonight,
trying to get rid of that thing...
and doing it all
in front of witnesses.
What would you have done
if the car hadrt broken down?
You couldn't set up
this trap.
Well, I guess we would have
found some other way.
You know what this place
reminds me of?
Just seeing all these cars...
You know, in our neighborhood,
we had a bunch ofjokers.
I mean, we were
a real wild bunch of guys.
And we figured out a perfect way
to put a car out of commission.
You take a potato,
you stick it in the exhaust pipe.
It doesn't cause any damage,
but the car won't start.
It was a terrible thing to do.
And I got a feeling...
that the reason I became a cop
was to make up for all those jokes
I played when I was a kid.